[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the shorter note on atta.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the Arhat's reflection, what appears reflexively is only pañca-khandhā, which he calls myself, simply for want of any other term.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, Tujana's reflection, what appears reflexively, is pañcupādānakkhandhā, or sakāya.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sakāya, when it appears reflexively, appears, in one way or another, as being
[SPEAKER_01]: The patujana confuses, as the arhat does not, the self-identity of the simple reflection, as with a mirror, where the same thing is seen from two points of view at once.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It may not be exactly obvious, you know, the simile given here is kind of on a coarse level of like looking at yourself in a mirror.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, I was hoping you could explain more about what exactly it entails to have a thing to be seen from two points of view at once, because that may not be obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: People may think I only see one thing, one view at once, my view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, in order to develop, to get the notion of that,
[SPEAKER_02]: Properly, a person needs to, needs to start recognizing what a, what a phenomenon is.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, they need, they need to learn how to allow things to arise and endure.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the important aspect here, enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because usually people regard presence of something when you think about it, but then if you're not directly attending it, you sort of
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you forget about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you think about it again, you think of it as if it's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, allowing thoughts, feelings, intentions, basically allowing phenomena that has arisen to endure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, for example, you can have a certain enduring mood that you are in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Despite the particular manifestations throughout the day, despite the particular actions, your mood remains the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's the same mood that has been enduring
[SPEAKER_02]: Throughout the day, changing on a particular level, while remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I say that's important, because only then, in relation to to an enduring phenomena, you can practice proper reflection, whereby you can see it's still enduring even much later, if it's still the same phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which then brings you to the to the next point of discernment, which is recognizing that
[SPEAKER_02]: The immediacy of the phenomena is a point of view, in the same sense that reflecting upon the immediacy of that phenomena is another simultaneous point of view, which is any... it's in the core of any process of thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whenever you think, you step back to a degree.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being able to step back in regard to your own thoughts, in regard to your own actions, means there is a possibility to step back, which means there is that whole dimension of reflection,
[SPEAKER_02]: That, as Yanavira said, remains perpetually available.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you practice reflecting, as in, you practice stepping back into it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That doesn't mean you interfere or you try to change the original object that's enduring in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you just start reflecting upon it while it is still there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that means seeing that same thing from two points of view at once.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, related to that, then, in the note A, he writes, in immediate experience, the thing is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: In reflexive experience, the thing is again present, but as implicit in a more in general thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, in reflection, the thing is twice present, once immediately and once reflexively.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is true of reflection both in the loose sense, as in reflection, with that C, or discursive thinking,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is already a degree of stepping back, which allows you that space to look at what you've been thinking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: But usually, people are too absorbed with whatever is in their immediacy, that even the acts of reflection, even elaborate acts of reflection, remain completely... they remain completely unaware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you describe exactly what is meant by an experience being immediate?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, whatever is present in front of you, whatever is present within your experience, whatever has arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's always some basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: For your thinking, for your intentions, for your feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: That basis is the immediacy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your situation, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what... that's what immediacy means.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're always in a situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the Buddha encouraged the mindfulness of the bodily postures.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because those are the fundamental setups of your situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: The way your body is deposited there, literally.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that determines a whole set of possible intentions and possible directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the next paragraph, he's discussing the difference between like the self-identity of a thing, like the same thing, versus the idea of self as the subject.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I guess the assumption, it seemed to me, was that maybe a patujana conceives his self-enduring as the self-same thing, but then kind of adds more than is actually there, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing can be created.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, patujana cannot invent and create
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a phenomenon that's completely independent of the five aggregates, or his experience as a whole, or his situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even the sense of self, the complete mistake of Pūtugina, is real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: That thing that Pūtugina takes as self, is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what the New Yorker points at.
[SPEAKER_02]: He says that it's the self-sameness of a thing that appears in immediacy and reflection, that Pūtugina confuses for his self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even that self of Puthujjana is there as a phenomena, but the mistake, it's not like negating that phenomena, the mistake is appropriating it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what Puthujjana needs to do is stop taking that selfness of a self-same thing seen in reflection and immediacy at the same time, stop taking that self as his own.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what achieves that through this reflexive act?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: By reflecting, you would see that immediacy and reflection are inseparable.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, the given situation and the pretty much your ability to be conscious of a given situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're paired right to the bone.
[SPEAKER_02]: They just cannot occur apart from each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: They cannot even be conceived apart from each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you realize that any notion of self that arises, arises on account of that determination.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: It becomes inconceivable for it to be mine, as in independent of all this that's in front of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's it's the very lack of reflection upon that, that's the reason for for Putrajana still maintaining the notion of ownership and appropriation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the third paragraph, Jnanavira mentions about how the patujana assumes that things are mine because I am, whereas Sotāpanna sees that I am because things are mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he describes the significance in presenting themselves as mine,
[SPEAKER_01]: As, eh... this significance, or intention, or determination, mine or for me, is in a sense a void, a negative aspect of the present thing, or existing phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it simply points to a subject, and the patujana, not seeing impermanence, or more specifically, not seeing the impermanence of this ubiquitous determination, deceives himself into supposing that there actually exists a subject, self,
[SPEAKER_01]: Independent of the object, which, later, as the nitya-sampana well understands, is merely the positive aspect of the phenomena, that which is for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: In this way, may we see in the patujana's experience, pañcupādānakkhandhā, as a negative aspect, the subject, and a positive aspect, the object.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it seems to me then that what this is referring to is partly
[SPEAKER_01]: Talking about how to attend things properly, because he's talking about things pointing to a subject, but one has to figure out how to understand something pointing, I guess, without looking where it's pointing, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it is that... it's that... that's what sense of appropriation is bound with.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things appear for...
[SPEAKER_02]: for a purpose, for something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the the atmas, the most general, or the most fundamental, the subtlest purpose is, even if a thing is completely without any practical purpose, it still has a purpose to appear for.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then Bhutujana would finish that assumption, because he already has that gratuitous view of me and I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he would just, ah, it appears for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that immediately already implies the entire appropriation of the entire sense base, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you were to see that nothing can appear without functioning physical senses working there, that beyond your control, eh... things cannot, couldn't appear for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But by not seeing that, then you just naturally, with the grain, assume
[SPEAKER_02]: That the appearance, the mere appearance of things, well, they might not be mine, but at least these perceptions are mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: These, the sight, sound, smell, taste, touches are mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they appear for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't appear for somebody else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the assumption of that me, that he's not really justified in making.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, once the assumption of self-view is undone, it cannot come back, because there was never room for it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: But not knowing that, you actually created that room.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, as the Buddha said, that mistake, that assumption, is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there was no first point before which a person wasn't ignorant and then they became ignorant and developed the self-view.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, although it shouldn't be there, if it's fully understood, it won't be there, but by not knowing that, you place it there, you assume it's being there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, the being is a result of your assumption, as in bhava comes from upadāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when we say, for me, it sounds like you're saying that it's kind of a more fundamental thing, like a thing being, like, mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's like an extra step, but in the same direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's, it's just, it's, it's...
[SPEAKER_02]: Being mine is the extension of, for me, being for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because being for me implies the possibility of being mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means you could regard for me as a very, very subtle form of conceiving as mine already.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you at least conceive it as a possible to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he goes on to clarify further with regards to the fact that the, eh... Patujan's experience has the subject and the object.
[SPEAKER_01]: But care is needed, for in fact, the division subject-object is not a simple negative-positive division.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it were, only the positive would be present as a distinct phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: And negative, the subject is not present at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: They simply not exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the subject is, in a sense, phenomenal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is an existing phenomenal negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: A negative that appears.
[SPEAKER_01]: The patujana asserts the present reality of his self.
[SPEAKER_01]: The irreplaceable being that I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact is that the intention or determination mind, pointing to a subject,
[SPEAKER_01]: It is this master whom the Pitujana, when he engages in reflection, is seeking to identify in vain.
[SPEAKER_01]: This delusive mastery of subject over object must be rigorously distinguished from the reflexive power of control or choice as exercised in voluntary action by kutujana and arhant alike.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess it's more than just like having a view.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, people get mystical about one's sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, they say that I am the knower, the witness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at the same time, they're bringing up that idea of them as a witness.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that extent, they have this weird hybrid, you know, positive and negative simultaneous thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it is, and it seems, kind of, liable to mystification.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does seem to go beyond both domains.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it is, it's, it's, it's structurally supported, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Through that implication of ownership, you end up also tacitly, sort of, implying that there, there is the owner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because why, why would then everything be manifested for, with the purpose of being owned and for somebody, for something, if there is nobody there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that mistake is beginningless, it means a putujana doesn't get to think from the right point of view first, and then develops a mistake.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's the mistake.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why he can't see.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even when he thinks about, oh, there is nobody there, he takes that as that which is there, as a self-centered phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, you can mystify it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can... you can deny it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can do whatever you want with it, and you still will be regarding it as mine, as an... and as my sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want...
[SPEAKER_01]: I wanted to ask about this last sentence from the note.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it goes, this delusive mastery of subject over object must be rigorously distinguished from a reflexive power of control or choice that is exercised voluntarily in action by Pitujana, Narhant alike.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: How is it exactly that one can make choices about things?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it seems like I am choosing, while at the same time, it seems, he's saying the arahant is also making choices, but for him it's a different affair.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's what's in common to both arahant and putujana.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the choice, the power of choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's structural.
[SPEAKER_02]: It belongs to five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the power revealed through the simultaneously arisen options, different possibilities that determine what the present thing is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's something that both Kutujana and Arahant have.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the problem with having that mistake of ownership
[SPEAKER_02]: Inevitably, that kind of... because choices are relatively subtle in comparison to other course of perceptions and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it will inevitably gravitate towards that center of the assumed self, as in, I am making these choices.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am deciding this, or I'm deciding that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, it just keeps reinforcing them, that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: The notion of mastery needs maintenance, and that maintenance is provided through, like, choosing preferences.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want this over, over, over, over that, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, eh... Arahant removes ownership in regard to the whole structure of the five aggregates, in regard to the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, no amount of, eh... volition and intentional action and thinking can induce that mistake again, because he is
[SPEAKER_02]: Fully penetrated and fully understood it and and and saw that it's simply there is no room for any sense of self or any ownership there, to any extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: The last thing I wanted to bring up was come from a footnote c basically talking about the elusiveness of that subject.
[SPEAKER_01]: He writes in footnote c
[SPEAKER_01]: But the positive negativity of the subject, which is what concerns us here, is by no means a simple affair.
[SPEAKER_01]: The subject presents itself, at the same time, certainly more elusive, yet no... as no less real than the object.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is our... is our task here to, eh... make this self not elusive anymore?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: The task is to learn how to see that sense of self as elusive, how to see it as an elusive phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: The task is to stop trying to overly define it or see it as a thing that's object of your perception, because it's always in the background.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because for as long as you have those assumptions that you can find it on the level of perceiving it directly, you are disqualifying yourself from actually being able to see it, because it can only be seen on its own terms, and those terms are the terms of an elusive phenomenon, an ambiguous background phenomena, and you have to start seeing it as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you realize you don't need to see it in any more defined manner, because
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether it's an elusive phenomena, whether it's a clear phenomena, whether it's the phenomena in the immediacy or the reflection, the foreground, the background, phenomena is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter what kind of it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what you want to be discerning.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you can start including that sense of self, no matter how elusive it is.